Guide to the Montana Student Nurses' Association Records 1948-2000
Montana Historical Society Archives
Montana Student Nurses' Association Records
1948-2000
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 318
Montana Student Nurses' Association
.8 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana Student Nurses' Association (MSNA) is a branch of the National Student Nurses Assocation. These records (1948-2000) consist of correspondence (1962-1997); minutes (1976-1997, scattered); organizational papers (1972-2000), including bylaws and membership records; printed material; and subject files (1948-1997).
The Montana Student Nurses' Association (MSNA) is a statewide voluntary membership organization composed of students enrolled in nursing education programs, leading to licensing as registered nurses, as well as already registered nurses continuing their education toward a baccalaureate degree. Prior to 1947 student nurses attended annual conventions of the Montana Nurses Association (MNA). In 1947 they formed their own organization, an affiliate of the National Student Nurses Association (NSNA). During the first years students developed bylaws and a structure for the operation of the organization and held two statewide meetings a year, one of which was held in conjunction with MNA. Since the 1950's a "Student Nurse of the Year" award is given annually by MNA which recognizes a student for outstanding nursing qualities, leadership ability, scholastic achievement and contributions to MSNA. By 1952 all schools of nursing in the state were represented in MSNA with a membership close to 100. Membership increased to 244 by 1960.. They published a newsletter, "White Caps" highlighting activities of students in the several schools In 1998 the name of the newsletter was changed to "Heart Beats" which had previously been the name of the MSU, Billings chapter newsletter. Several nursing students attended NSNA conventions during the 1950s but participation dropped during the 1960's and 1970's as hospital schools of nursing closed. Interest in MSNA increased during the 1980's and today there is a viable organization with chapters at the state's two collegiate nursing programs, Montana State University (MSU) in Bozeman and Carroll College in Helena. At both the national and state levels, students now plan programs and activities focusing on issues that affect them as students and future members of the nursing profession. Several MSNA members have served as officers of the national organization, including Wendy Blakley elected secretary in 1974; Lynne Riley elected to the Board of Directors; and Julie McGee, elected president 1992.
Content Description:
Records are arranged in six series: interoffice correspondence, general correspondence, minutes, organizational records, printed materials, and subject files. Interoffice correspondence (1962-1997) consists of letters or memos from the president or advisor of the Association to the membership and letters to MSNA officers from the national organization. General Correspondence (1977-1997) includes a small amount of miscellaneous correspondence. Minutes (1976-1997) include statewide conventions and scattered meetings of the Board of Directors. Organizational records (1972-2000) include membership lists, bylaws, individual campus material, and guidelines from NSNA. Printed material consists of scattered copies of newsletters (1962-1997) published by MSNA and "Heart Beat" (1988-1997) published by the Montana State University, Billings chapter. Subject files include a committee on legislative information (1980-1997); convention programs for both the state (1948-1974, scattered) and national organization (1980-1997); and records from the 1997 history project, including transcripts of oral history interviews. Miscellany includes a song and a poem. [The collection results from an Undergraduate Scholars Program project "Past 50 Years of MSNA" done in 1997 by nursing students Bridget Hickey and Kerri Klundt under the direction of Dr. Therese Sullivan.]
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Nurses; Nursing--Study and teaching; Montana; Medicine and Health
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - National Student Nurses Association and officers of Montana Student Nurses Association, 1962-1997 (Box-folder 1 / 1-2)
- General Correspondence
  - Chronological (correspondents include Lee Metcalf, Miriam Tournai, St. James Community Hospital, Hanna Wisniewski, Montana State University College of Nursing, Educational Resources, Mayo Foundation, University of Montana), 1977-1997 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
- Minutes
  - Annual meetings, 1976-1997 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Board of directors, 1976-1977, 1997 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Organizational Records
  - By-laws, 1972-1977, 2000 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Campus units: Carroll College (includes minutes), 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Campus units: Montana State University, Billings (includes newsletter, by-laws, quarterly reports), 1976-1983 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Campus units: Montana State University, Bozeman (includes minutes, newsletter), 1988, 1995 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Campus units: Great Falls (includes report), 1980 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Campus units: University of Montana, Missoula (includes newsletters, minutes), 1986-1987, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Montana membership lists, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 1 / 12-15)
  - Montana officers lists, 1993-1997 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - National membership statistics, 1984-1888 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - National presidents lists, guidelines, business books, policies, etc., 1979-1992, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 18)
- Printed Material
  - Newsletters (statewide, title varies, scattered issues only), 1962-1997 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Newsletters ("Heart Beat", Montana State University, Billings), 1988-1997 (Box-folder 2 / 2-3)
- Subject Files
  - Cancer workshop, 1996 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - Committee on Legislation, 1980-1997 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - History project: correspondence, 1997 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - History project: data and expenses, 1997 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - History project: "The Past 50 Years of the Montana Student Nurses' Association" (transcripts of oral histories with Harriet Hunthausen, Linda Olson, Wendy Blakely, Jon Carlson, Julie McGee, Rebecca Spear, Wade King), 1997 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Montana Student Nurses' Association convention programs, 1948, 1962 1972-1974 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - National Student Nurses' Association convention programs, 1980-1997 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Student Nurse of the Year contest, 1978, n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 11)
- Miscellany
  - "A Nurse's Poem," by Marilyn Malcolm; "M.S.N.A. Song", n.d. (Box-folder 2 / 12)